A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Inclusive Economies, Office Files of Laine Romero-Alston FA1376
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Inclusive Economies, Office Files of Laine Romero-Alston
1994-2018
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Romero-Alston, Laine
FA1376
2.75 Cubic Feet 7 document boxes: 6 letter size boxes and 1 legal size box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in two accessions in 2021 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2021:025 and 2021:083.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files Laine Romero-Alston created when she worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's inclusive economic development programs. Files document the progression of Romero-Alston's work at the Foundation from managing Next Generation Workforce Strategies grants in the Quality Employment unit of the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) to managing Quality Work and Economic Security (QWRS) grants in Inclusive Economies (IE). Romero-Alston also worked on the Foundation's Future of Work (FOW) initiative.
The collection consists of two series. Notebooks Romero-Alston created through her activities are contained in the first series. Romero-Alston's subject files are contained in the second series.
Files in the collection document Romero-Alston's leadership of the Ford Foundation's programming for supporting sustainable and inclusive workforce development. Grants and initiatives focused on global workers, immigrant and migrant workers, informal workers, service workers in various industries, low-wage workers, worker centers, labor unions, job quality, workers' rights, human rights, global labor, and global supply chains. There is a lot of focus on strategy and capacity building and the increasing global perspective of the Foundation's workforce development and job quality programming through the emergence of QWES in IE.
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, memos, notes, proposals, reports, meeting materials, drafts, budget spreadsheets, articles, and publications.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of two series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Laine Romero-Alston notebooks, 2013-2018
Series 2. Subject files, 1994-2018
Ford Foundation; Employee rights; Employment -- United States; Foreign workers--United States; Labor; Labor unions
- Laine Romero-Alston notebooks, 2013-2018; 1; .57 Cubic Feet 1.5 document boxes: 1.5 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains notebooks Laine Romero-Alston created when she worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's programming for inclusive economic development. The notebooks span across Romero-Alson's positions in Quality Employment in the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) and then Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) in Inclusive Economies (IE). Not all the notebooks in the series were clearly dated, so inferences were made from content in the notebooks when it was available. Efforts were not made to organize these notebooks chronologically because of their uncertain dates.
  Romero-Alston used the notebooks for meetings and trips, "to do" lists, job quality and workforce development program interests, and internal Ford Foundation activities.
  A few other items were inserted into the notebooks which document Romero-Alston's participation in different meetings and trips including agendas, itineraries, business cards, and correspondence.
  - December 2013-January 2014 notebook, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted – Open in 2025
  - July-November 2014 notebook (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - August-October 2014 notebook (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - September-October 2014 notebook (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - December 2014-January 2015 notebook, 2014-2015 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Restricted – Open in 2026
  - February-April 2015 notebook (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - April-December 2015 notebook (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - July-October 2015 notebook (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - December 2017-2018 notebook (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Restricted – Open in 2029
  - Undated notebook, circa 2017 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Restricted – Open in 2028
  - July 2016 notebook (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Restricted – Open in 2027
  - May 2016 notebook (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - January 2016 notebook (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Undated notebook, circa 2015 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Undated notepad (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Undated notebook (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fall 2017 notebook (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - December 2016-March 2017 notebook, 2016-2017 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - November 2015, September-November 2016 notebook, 2015-2016 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - EDGE (Engaged Donors for Global Equity) Funders Alliance Conference April 2018, New Orleans, Louisiana notebook (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Subject files, 1994-2018; 2; 2.18 Cubic Feet 5.5 document boxes: 4.5 letter size boxes and 1 legal size box
  This series contains the subject files Laine Romero-Alston created when she worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's programs for inclusive economic development. The subject files span across Romero-Alston's positions in Quality Employment in the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) and then Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) in Inclusive Economies (IE). The subject files in the series are organized by different themes including grantees, BUILD grantees, strategy and Theory of Change (TOC), global, budget, funders groups, Ford Foundation working groups, and Future of Work (FOW).
  Materials in the series document Romero-Alston's management of a grant portfolio regarding sustainable inclusive economic development and support of Ford Foundation program strategy development.
  Files in the series contain correspondence, notes, reports, proposals, meeting materials, drafts, articles, budget spreadsheets, and publications.
  - Grantees - Service Employers International Union (SEIU), 2016 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Grantees - Restaurant Opportunities Center (ROC) United, 2011-2014 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Grantees - National Day Laborer Organizing Network (NDLON), 2012 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Grantees - National Domestic Workers Alliance (NDWA), 2010-2016 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Grantees - 2016 transition (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Grantees - National Guestworker Alliance (NGA), 2017 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grantees - New Orleans, Louisiana, 2013-2014 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Grantees - The Care Institute, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Grantees - Workers Lab, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Grantees - Food system/chain work, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Grantees - Nail salon workers, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Grantees - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), 2012-2014 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - BUILD grants - General, 2015-2016 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - BUILD grants - National Day Laborer Organizing Network (NDLON), 2015-2016 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - BUILD grants - Restaurant Opportunities Center (ROC) United, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - BUILD grants - National Domestic Workers Alliance (NDWA), undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - BUILD grants - National Employment Law Project (NELP), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Readings, 2010-2013 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Strategic communication, 2016-2017 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Strategic communication, 2011-2013 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Deferred Action for Parental Accountability (DAPA)-Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals (DACA)/Comprehensive Immigration Reform (CIR), 2012-2015 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Revenue generation, 2015-2017 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Opposition readiness/RoadMap, 2012-2015 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Domestic outsourcing, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - On-demand economy, 2015-2016 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - Consumer engagement, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Strategy and Theory of Change - culture/CHANGE, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Global - Articles, general, 1995-2014 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Global - Informal workers, 1994-2015 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Global - Global strategy, 2012-2014 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Global - Forced labor, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Global - International Labor Organization (ILO), 2015-2016 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Global - Global labor/Supply chain, 2013-2015 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Global - International Labor Organization (ILO) Global Commission on the Future of Work (GCFOW), 2017 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Global - Inclusive Economies (IE) global strategy development and global supply chains (GSC), 2015-2017 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Global - Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) 2017 global strategy exploration, 2010-2017 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Global - Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) global strategy exploration Dalberg Advisors review, 2017-2018 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Next Generation Workforce Strategies (NGWS) budgets - Grant spreadsheets, 2011-2014 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Quality Employment budgets - Grant spreadsheets, 2012-2014 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Funders groups - United States southern worker labor strategy, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Funders groups - Neighborhood Funders Group (NFG), 2015 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Funders groups - Labor Innovations for the Twenty First Century (LIFT) Fund, 2016-2017 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Funders groups - Blue Mountain Center (BMC) New Economy retreat, 2007-2014 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Funders groups - Labor Innovations for the Twenty First Century (LIFT) Fund, 2011-2018 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Funders groups - Labor Innovations for the Twenty First Century (LIFT) Fund, 2011-2013 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Funders groups - Funders Network on Transforming the Global Economy (FNTG), 2008-2010 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Funders groups - Justice Funders Network (JFN)/Funders Collaborative on Youth Organizing (FYCO), 2012 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Funders groups - New York Social Justice Funders, 2011-2012 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Funders groups - Echo Justice, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Funders groups - Working Group on Labor and Community Partnerships (WGLCP), 2008-2013 (Box 6, Folder 70-71)
  - Ford Foundation working groups - States Working Group (SWG), 2014-2017 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Ford Foundation working groups - Contingent workers funders group, 2014-2015 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Ford Foundation working groups - New Orleans, Louisiana Working Group, 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Inclusive Economies (IE) strategy, 2016 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) 2017 grantmaking strategy, 2016-2017 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES) Lines of Work documents, 2016-2017 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Quality Work and Economic Security (QWES), 2014-2016 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - United States regional strategy, 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Future of Work (FOW) strategy, 2018 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Future of Work (FOW), 2012-2015 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Ford Foundation 2012 Annual Report, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 82)